<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[balls' blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://balasuar.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://balasuar.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-29T14:23:01-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://balasuar.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to the Jungle]]></title>
    <link href="http://balasuar.github.com/blog/2012/10/29/welcome-to-the-jungle/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-29T02:03:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://balasuar.github.com/blog/2012/10/29/welcome-to-the-jungle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Back again for the 1nd time.</h1>

<p>I&#8217;m trying yet another attempt at blogging. Maybe I&#8217;ll be successful this time. Either way it&#8217;s an excuse to play with some new technologies out. For this, I&#8217;m using Octopress. The folks behind Octopress claim it&#8217;s a &#8216;blog for hackers&#8217; but by hackers they really mean &#8216;blog for people who like to write code and or use scripts to get things done.&#8217; I definitely fall into the latter camp (though I&#8217;ve been known to reverse engineer the authentication schemes of mobile apps from time to time).</p>

<p>Currently, I&#8217;m Cofounder, and VP of Engineering for a young startup here in Seattle. My work consumes almost all my time, and so I&#8217;m not betting that I&#8217;ll be too successful with yet another blogging endeavor.</p>

<h3>Reality For Whom?</h3>

<p>Bravo has a new Reality Show coming out about startups in Silicon Valley. The sense I get from random internet noise is that this show isn&#8217;t going to be very popular. But as a new entrepreneur, I&#8217;m interested in seeing how it compares to my experiences.</p>

<p>Bravo has posted some preview clips, and I&#8217;ve seen a few. There is one about an [Investor Pitch][http://www.bravotv.com/start-ups-silicon-valley/season-1/videos/a-disrespectful-pitch] that piqued my interest.  With my role as a cofounder of a startup, I&#8217;ve been receiving a lot of hands long experience while learning about entrepreneurship, and the business side of a software company. One of the best parts of my job (there are a lot of them), is meeting with and pitching investors.</p>

<p>After watching the clip, my first reaction was &#8220;Meh.&#8221; It matches my experience&#8211;pitch meetings have a casual feel to them; you want a singular voice (though everyone should contribute to the conversation). However, Ben (the british guy) was wrong, you can&#8217;t expect an investor pitch to follow a specific plan. Some investor meetings, we&#8217;ve walked through the pitch deck, others we jumped right into the product, some investors wanted to talk &#8220;Go To Market Strategies&#8221;, others about getting to the Series-A round. So far what I&#8217;ve learned is to that investors have a variety of things their interested in, and while there are some commonalities to meetings, they&#8217;re way more dictated by the personalities and experiences of the person(s) we&#8217;re pitching. When Ben feels disrespected by the investor reading the deck at his own pace, it comes across like whining.</p>

<p>When watching the clip, I ignored the pacing of the meeting&#8211;reality tv shows are notorious about edits and cuts to make something seem like it has more tension and thus more drama than it really does. Even the most &#8220;adversarial&#8221; meetings had a pleasant approach to it. So long as you come in understanding that the people you&#8217;re talking to are very busy, are pitched all the time, and thus should value and respect their time.</p>

<p>So overall, I think the show could be interesting. Some of the other clips about partying, and life outside of the office don&#8217;t match my experiences but I do plan on giving the show a try. Maybe I can use a weekly recap as a way to force myself into blogging more regularly?</p>

<p>Survey Says&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
